<?xml version="1.0"?>
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><MetaID>{E24FD2C8-5995-4E28-A28F-F04CA5DF68A2}</MetaID><CreaDate>20090812</CreaDate><CreaTime>15443900</CreaTime><SyncOnce>TRUE</SyncOnce><ModDate>20150521</ModDate><ModTime>121436</ModTime><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><ArcGISProfile>FGDC</ArcGISProfile></Esri><toolbox name="DasymetricToolbox" alias="IDM"><summary><para>A dasymetric map seeks to display statistical surface data by exhaustively partitioning space into zones where the zone boundaries reflect the underlying statistical surface variation. The process of dasymetric mapping is the transformation of data from a set of arbitrary source zones to a dasymetric map via the overlay of the source zones with an ancillary data set. In practice, dasymetric mapping is often considered a particular type of areal interpolation technique where source zone data are excluded from certain classes in a categorical ancillary data set. Dasymetric mapping is applicable to a wide variety of tasks where the user seeks to refine spatially aggregated data, for example in estimating local population characteristics in areas where only coarser, regional resolution census data are available. This tool addresses the design, implementation, validation, and application of a new ‘intelligent’ dasymetric mapping (IDM) technique that supports a variety of methods for characterizing the relationship between the ancillary data and underlying statistical surface. The technique is referred to as intelligent because an analyst may establish this relationship subjectively using their own domain knowledge, extract this relationship from the data using a novel empirical sampling technique, or combine the subjective and empirically-based methods.</para><para>This toolbox contains a number of scripts that assist preparing vector population and raster ancillary datasets for intelligent dasymetric mapping, performs the dasymetric calculations, and then generates a floating point output raster of revised population density.  Please see the documentation on the individual tools for more information.  </para></summary><arcToolboxHelpPath>c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.3\Help\gp</arcToolboxHelpPath><toolsets/></toolbox><dataIdInfo><idCitation xmlns=""><resTitle>DasymetricToolbox</resTitle><citRespParty xmlns=""><rpIndName>Torrin Hultgren</rpIndName><rpOrgName>CSC/US EPA</rpOrgName><rpPosName>GIS Analyst</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="">010</RoleCd></role><rpCntInfo><cntAddress><delPoint>79 TW Alexander Blvd</delPoint><city>Research Triangle Park</city><adminArea>North Carolina</adminArea><postCode>27709</postCode><eMailAdd>hultgren.torrin@epa.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo></citRespParty></idCitation><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This toolbox contains a number of scripts that assist preparing vector population and raster ancillary datasets for intelligent dasymetric mapping, performs the dasymetric calculations, and then generates a floating point output raster of revised population density. Please see the documentation on the individual tools for more information.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs><resConst><Consts xmlns=""><useLimit>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The author of this script assumes no liability for the quality nor the appropriate application of this code. Please make sure you fully understand the process before attempting to draw conclusions from the results.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</useLimit></Consts></resConst><themeKeys><keyword>population</keyword><keyword>areal interpolation</keyword><keyword>pycnophylactic</keyword><keyword>dasymetric</keyword></themeKeys><descKeys KeyTypCd="005"><keyTyp><keyTyp>005</keyTyp></keyTyp><keyword>population</keyword><keyword>areal interpolation</keyword><keyword>pycnophylactic</keyword><keyword>dasymetric</keyword></descKeys><searchKeys><keyword>population</keyword><keyword>areal interpolation</keyword><keyword>pycnophylactic</keyword><keyword>dasymetric</keyword></searchKeys><idPurp>Toolbox for Intelligent Dasymetric Mapping</idPurp><dataExt xmlns=""><geoEle xmlns=""><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"/></geoEle></dataExt><dataChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></dataChar><idStatus><ProgCd value="001"/></idStatus></dataIdInfo><distInfo><distributor><distorFormat><formatName>ArcToolbox Toolbox</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdContact xmlns=""><rpIndName>Torrin Hultgren</rpIndName><rpPosName>GIS Analyst</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="006">010</RoleCd></role><rpCntInfo xmlns=""><cntAddress addressType=""><city>Research Triangle Park</city><adminArea>North Carolina</adminArea><postCode>27709</postCode><eMailAdd>hultgren.torrin@epa.gov</eMailAdd></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><displayName>Torrin Hultgren</displayName></mdContact></metadata>
